## Carly A. Strasser, PhD

ContactEmail: carlystrasser@gmail.comWebsite: strasser.github.ioInformationPhone: 805.616.3585LinkedIn: Carly Strasser

## **Summary**

Creative, independent leader with strengths in program development, strategic thinking, and implementing novel solutions to problems in spaces adjacent to scientific research. Skilled in forging partnerships, aligning activities with organizational goals, facilitating development of tools and resources for better research, and connecting individuals to accelerate the progress of science.

# Professional Experience

## Chan Zuckerberg Initiative, San Francisco CA

Senior Program Manager, Open Science

May 2020 - Present

Drive the execution of open science initiatives for the Open Science program at CZI. Develop strategies for promoting and enabling more transparent and reproducible science through international funding portfolios. Work closely with community, industry, and funder partners to ensure programmatic impact. Manage the development and operations of grant programs to support open science, including designing and executing requests for proposals, driving targeted grants, and tracking and reporting grantee progress. Run workshops and undertake landscaping activities to inform future grant making.

#### Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle WA

Director of Alliances and Data Strategy

July 2018 - April 2020

As a core leader of Chief Data Officer's department, established and led strategic initiatives supporting data-intensive research at Fred Hutch through internal and external partnerships, community building, and infrastructure development. Co-led engagements with external partners including the Seattle Cancer Care Alliance, Microsoft Research, and BC Cancer. Contributed to strategic growth plan for the department, including establishing new teams and roles, and recruiting new staff to engage researchers to understand their needs. Overhauled program operations and communications to ensure effective information sharing, staff engagement, and program efficacy.

### Collaborative Knowledge Foundation (Coko), San Francisco CA

Director of Strategic Development

December 2017 - June 2018

Established and managed the development of the Coko community program across all publishing products and services. Worked with marketing team, developers, and product managers to effectively communicate Coko's mission of creating open source infrastructure for research communication.

#### Gordon & Betty Moore Foundation, Palo Alto CA

Program Officer

March 2015 - December 2017

Implemented and managed the Data-Driven Discovery Initiative alongside the Program Director. Administered grants in the Initiative's portfolio; planned and oversaw grantee meetings, collaborations, and partnerships; and tracked trends, synthesizing knowledge relevant to the Initiative. Separate from the Initiative, sourced and developed grants related to improving how science is conducted, including projects focused on data management, scholarly communication, and synthesis studies. Led establishment of an Open Access Policy for all grantees.

## California Digital Library, University of California Office of the President, Oakland CA

Research Data Specialist

July 2011 - March 2015

Provided expert guidance and consultation on data stewardship to UC researchers; led workshops and gave seminars on the value of data management for scientists; promoted open science and open data within

the UC and beyond. Initially charged with product development in partnership with Microsoft Research, working alongside remote engineers to develop the data curation tool DataUp. Dash (now Dryad) data curation platform product manager; DMPTool (dmptool.org) project team member. Supervisor, CLIR/DLF Postdoctoral Fellow in Data Curation. Briefly (6 months) seconded by DataCite (datacite.org) to serve as Manager of Strategic Partnerships, with a focus on building relationships with European partners and members of the organization.

DataONE, based at National Center for Ecological Analysis & Synthesis, UC Santa Barbara

Postdoctoral Associate

September 2010 - August 2011

Engaged the scientific and data management community in the Data Observation Network for Earth (DataONE), an NSF-funded cyber-infrastructure project to provide universal access to environmental and ecological data. Conducted research related to data education, organized and led workshops, and participated in working groups.

University of Alberta & Dalhousie University, Edmonton AB & Halifax NS, Canada

Postdoctoral Investigator

January 2009 - October 2010

Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, Woods Hole MA

Postdoctoral Investigator

March 2008 - December 2008

#### Education

## Massachusetts Institute of Technology/Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution Ph.D., Biological Oceanography

## University of San Diego

B.A., Marine Science with Biology emphasis

## Relevant Publications

**C Strasser**, K Hertweck, J Greenberg, D Taraborelli, and E Vu. 2022. Ten simple rules for funding scientific open source software. *PLOS Computational Biology* 18(11): 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1010627.

K Hertweck and **C Strasser**. 2020. From novice to expert: Supporting all levels of computational expertise in reproducible research methods. PEARC '20: Practice and Experience in Advanced Research Computing. 10.1145/3311790.3396655.

L Teytelman, W Gunn and J Kamens (authorship limited to 3). 2019. The EPA's proposed 'transparency rule' will harm health, safety, and the environment. *STAT*, December 9 2019. www.statnews.com/2019/12/09/epa-transparency-rule-bad-for-science-health-safety-environment.

S Alexander, K Jones, N Bennett, A Budden, M Cox, M Crosas, E Game, J Geary, R Hardy, J Johnson, S Karcher, N Motzer, J Pittman, H Randell, J Silva, P Pinto da Silva, **C Strasser**, C Strawhacker, A Stuhl and N Weber. 2019. Qualitative data sharing and synthesis for sustainability science. *Nature Sustainability*. 10.1038/s41893-019-0434-8.

J Chodacki, P Cruse, J Lin, C Neylon, D Pattinson, and **C Strasser**. 2018. *Supporting Research Communications: A Guide*. Book available for download on Zenodo. 10.5281/zenodo.3524662 (open access).

**C Strasser** and E Khare. 2017. Estimated effects of implementing an open access policy for grantees at a private foundation. *PeerJ* 5:e3853 10.7717/peerj.3853. (open access).

**C Strasser**. 2016. Preprints: The Bigger Picture. *Authoria* July 26, 2016. 10.15200/winn.146955.56313 (open access).

**C Strasser** and 22 others. 2016. Preprints for the life sciences. *Science* 352: 6288. pp. 889-901. 10.1126/science.aaf9133 (open access with login).

**C Strasser**. 2015. Research Data Management: A Primer Publication of the National Information Standards Organization. Download from www.niso.org (open access).

J Kratz and **C Strasser**. 2015. Making data count. *Nature Scientific Data* 2: 150039. 10.1038/sdata.2015.39 (open access).

J Kratz and **C Strasser**. 2015. Researcher Perspectives on Publication and Peer Review of Data. *PLoS ONE* 10(2): e0117619. 10.1371/journal.pone.0117619 (open access).

J Lin and **C Strasser**. 2014. Recommendations for the Role of Publishers in Access to Data. *PLoS Biology* 12(10): e1001975. 10.1371/journal.pbio.1001975 (open access).

J Kratz and **C Strasser**. 2014. Data publication consensus and controversies. *F1000Research* 3:94. 10.12688/f1000research.3979.3 (open access).

**C Strasser**, J Kunze, S Abrams, and P Cruse. 2014. DataUp: A tool to help researchers describe and share tabular data. *F1000 Research* 3:6. 10.12688/f1000research.3-6.v2 (open access).

J Hartter, SJ Ryan, CA MacKenzie, JN Parker, and **CA Strasser**. 2013. Spatially Explicit Data: Stewardship and Ethical Challenges in Science. *PLoS Biology* 11(9): e1001634. 10.1371/journal.pbio.1001634 (open access).

S Hampton, **CA Strasser**, J Tewksbury, W Gram, A Budden, A Batcheller, C Duke, and J Porter. 2013. Big data and the future of ecology. *Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment* 11(3): 156-162. 10.1890/120103. Open access copy.

S Hampton, **C Strasser**, and J Tewksbury. 2013. Growing Pains for Ecology in the  $21^{st}$  Century. *BioScience*. 63(2): 69-71. 10.1525/bio.2013.63.2.2 (open access).

**CA Strasser** and SE Hampton. 2012. The Fractured Lab Notebook: Undergraduates and Ecological Data Management Training in the United States. *Ecopshere* 3:art116. 10.1890/ES12-00139.1 (open access).

S Hampton, J Tewksbury and **CA Strasser**. 2012. Ecological data in the Information Age. Guest Editorial in *Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment* 10:59. 10.1890/1540-9295-10.2.59 (open access).

A full list of publications is available at strasser.github.io